<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached in the High Church of Edinburgh, June 9th, 1695 before His Grace the Marquess of Tweddale His Majesties High Commissioner and before many of the nobility, barrons and burrows, members of the High Court of Parliament, and the magistrates of the said city / by David Williamson ...</title>
            <author>Williamson, David, d. 1706.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 71 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66476</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W2797</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8132</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12529445</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12529445</idno>
            <idno type="VID">62741</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66476)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 62741)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 952:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached in the High Church of Edinburgh, June 9th, 1695 before His Grace the Marquess of Tweddale His Majesties High Commissioner and before many of the nobility, barrons and burrows, members of the High Court of Parliament, and the magistrates of the said city / by David Williamson ...</title>
                  <author>Williamson, David, d. 1706.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>27, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by George Mosman and are to be sold at his shop ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:62741:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:62741:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached in the High Church of EDINBURGH, June 9th 1695. Before HIS GRACE The Marqueſs of TWEDDALE HIS MAJESTIES <hi>High Commiſſioner</hi> And before many of the Nobility, Barrons and Burrows, Members of the High Court of Parliament, And the Magiſtrates of the ſaid City</p>
            <p>By <hi>David Williamſon</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel at the <hi>Weſt-kirk.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>EDINBURGH, Printed by <hi>George Moſman</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop in the <hi>Parliament-cloſs.</hi> 1695.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:62741:2"/>
            <head>GOOD READER.</head>
            <p>The Author being threatned by ſome. that they would cauſe Print his Sermon, as written from his Mouth (however uncorrect it might be) And that ſeverals had made wrong accounts of the matter ſpoken; He was preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed upon theſe Reaſons, by Friends; to offer a correct Coppy to the Preſs, Which he condeſcended to do upon their Importunity, without alteration of words or Sentences.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:62741:2"/>
            <head>The Text</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Iſaiah <hi>Chapter 38.3:</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And ſaid, Remember now, O Lord, I beſeech thee, how I have walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before thee, in truth, and with a perfect heart, and have done that which is good in thy ſight: and <hi>Hezekiah</hi> wept ſore.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>HEzekiah</hi> was a Good Man, a Great Man, a Rare Man, a Praying King. Of all the Three and twenty Kings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Judah,</hi> before, and after the Schiſme, Wee find only Nine commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for Good. <hi>viz. David, Solomon, Aſa, Jehoſaphat, Amaſiah, Azariah, Jotham, Hezekiah, Joſiah:</hi> Of the Twenty Kings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> after the Rent, Wee find none commended for Good, but only <hi>Jehu,</hi> commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for cutting off the houſe <hi>Ahab</hi> and deſtroying the Worſhippers of <hi>Baal</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:62741:3"/>2 <hi>Kings</hi> 9.10. Yet was he reproved for cleaving to the Sins of <hi>Jeroboam</hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 10.31.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hezekiah</hi> was a Good King, but not faultleſs, his Heart was lifted up with Pride, and he Pay'd dear for it, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> chap. 20. verſes 14. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Nor did his Goodneſs exeeme him from Trouble; in the preceeding Chapter he was ſore diſtreſſed by a ſeige, and now ſick unto Death.</p>
            <p>The words contain his fervent Prayer; I ſhall not trouble you with te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious Explication, nor Curious Diviſion.</p>
            <p n="1">1. He Prays that the Lord would Remember him, not that God is ſubject to forgetfulneſs, but he would have the Lord effectually to mind him, according to his promiſe made to <hi>Abraham</hi> when he indented with him <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.1.2. <hi>Walk before me,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>and he thou perfect,</hi> I am God Almighty, <hi>And I will make my Covenant between me and thee, and I will multiply thee exceedingly:</hi> Now he had in ſome meaſure (Human Frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty excepted) kept the condition there required. 2. He reflects on his Heart and Way, I <hi>have walked before thee;</hi> That is, under the awful apprehenſions of an Omniſcient every-where preſent God: <hi>In truth and with aperfect heart,</hi> It's the ſame on the matter with ſimplicity and Godly ſincerity 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.12. Mentioned in oppoſition to Carnal policy, called there fleſhly Wiſdom; Would he ſay, I have ſtudied to be ſincerely and honeſtly minded, and am not conſcious of groſs Exorbitancies in my courſe, which uſes to ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en Mens Days. 3. Wee have the proof of his Sincerity in a Good Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, <hi>I have done that which is good in thy ſight.</hi> 4. Wee have his preſent Melancholy temper. <hi>and Hezekiah wept ſore,</hi> for Deaths aſpect was not pleaſant to him, he would ſam have lived a while longer, either to have throughed the begun Reformation, or forſeeing what might follow to Church and ſtate upon his removal, eſpecially they being for preſent in a diſtracted miſerable condition, or probably he Scunnered at Death, as na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture will do in the beſt of Saints.</p>
            <p>I ſhall only take up this one point from the words.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doct. That theſe who would expect comfort at Death, muſt make conſcience of a ſincere Religious walk in their life.</hi> Whoſe Heart condemns them not in <hi>this</hi> may be very confident of <hi>that.</hi> I ſhall ſpeak to thoſe three Branches. 1. of Death. 2. of Uprightneſs. 3. of a Religious walk.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt for Death, I would ſay theſe five things. 1. It is certain it is appointed for all Men to dye, and but once <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.27. All are born with the ſeeds of Death in their boſom; The prophaneſt Atheiſt, who defyes Death, ſhall not ſhift it when his day cometh.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:62741:3"/>
            <p n="2">2. It is certain Death is uncertain. 1. As to the place where, at home or abroad, by Sea or by Land. 2. As to the manner how, a violent or na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rural Death, ſudden or lingering. 3. As to the time when, wee read of no Man who ever got a leaſe of their time, but this <hi>Hezekiah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. It's certain Death waits no Mans readineſs, if a Man be not prepared, that Meſſenger when he cometh will not defer one moment.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Death cannot properly be ſaid to be a ſurprize to Believers in Chriſt, it may be ſudden, the Chriſtan not being in that frame and Exerciſe deſir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, may fall ſhort of Conſolation, but his ſtate being ſure, his Salvation is ſecured.</p>
            <p n="5">5. It is certain we may have a day better and another worſe, in time, but after Death there is no change, Eternal Well or Eternal Wo, where the Tree falls there it Lyes <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 11.3.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> 1. Wee ſhall make ſome practical improvement of this: And 1. Be convinced, That this Tyrant Death is the indiſpenſible fatality of all Men; Altho' ſome adjourn the thouh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s of it, which is their ſin and folly, and they may be refuted from the conſideration of the frequent warnings of Mortality and the ſhortneſs of time compared to an Hand-breadth <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39.5. To a Vapour <hi>Jam.</hi> 4.14. to the fading Graſs 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.24. Yet many put that Day far away <hi>Amos</hi> 6.3. teaſing up their thoughts, anent the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of their Riches, the ſtanding of their Family, the advancement of their Honour, the filling of their Cup of pleaſure, and before they are aware Death puts in the ſickle, and their Breath goes out, they return to their duſt, &amp; in that day their Thoughts periſh, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſal.</hi> 14.6, 4, 5. their fair white thoughts as the word is all their deſigns &amp; endeavours, either for themſelves or others. O if people would take leaſure but to Commune with their own Hearts, till they had ſome impreſſion and preſent Heart-affecting thoughts of Death, then reflecting on their way in the World, for the World, they would conclude, that all their Labour amounted to no more, than what is imported in that Verdict <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 1.2. <hi>Vanity of Vanitys, all is Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nty and Voxation of Spuit;</hi> Then ſhould Self-deſigning-men, &amp; Self-deceivers whoſe deſires, deſigns and endeavours, did riſe no higher then <hi>Self,</hi> find that they had played the fool and cheat to their own Souls, when their hearts ſhall overcaſt, with the confuſion of theſe thoughts and challenges, that they ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ned in due time to intertain,</p>
            <p>Altho' death be in the Creed, yet it is not in many peoples belief, ſuch as. 1. The ſtupid and ſecure, who are not moved with Terrours and threatnings, like to thoſe of <hi>Noah</hi> his days, who did eat and drink till
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:62741:4"/>the flood came, <hi>Math.</hi> 24.38.39. 2ly. The worldly minded, whoſe time and cares are Swallowed up with vanities of this life, as if they were never to ſeparat, like the man <hi>Luck</hi> 12. 3ly The proud, and Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dees of the worldmind not they will be laid in the Duſt, where their bones will bear no badge of their Gentility, Theſe, with the worldly, go far in the way to Hell for their honour and profit. 4ly. Thoſe who are careleſſe to trim their Lamps, and get intereſt in Chriſt and live as never to dye.</p>
            <p>I Would preſs upon you <hi>all,</hi> frequent and ſerious thoughts of Death from theſe conſiderations 1. Believing thoughts of Death would aquaint you with it before it come, which were your advantage, to make it the eaſier, &amp; Leſs terrifying when it comes; Were you Seaſoning your Hearts with the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Evening thoughts of it every day. 2ly. It would make you dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent in hearing of the word, not knowing but every Sermon may be the Laſt, the Lord knows, this may be the Laſt to ſome who hears me.</p>
            <p n="3">3ly. It would let you ſee an end of all perfections <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119 96. That theſe who call their Lands by their Names, Their honour deſcends not to the grave with them <hi>Pſal.</hi> 49.11.17. Nor will their <hi>Grandure</hi> diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaiſh their <hi>Duſt</hi> from the <hi>Beggers, Job.</hi> 21.26, They all lye down alike in the Grave. 4ly This would ſtir up to excelent thoughts of God, there be ſome, <hi>God is not in all their thoughts, Pſal.</hi> 10.4 Becauſe Death is not in them <hi>Job,</hi> 19. When <hi>Job.</hi> ſpeaks of the <hi>Worms</hi> he has exalting thoughts of God. 5ly. It would make People more uſefull to others, and better neighbours, It would make meek in paſſing injuries, watchfull againſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering of them <hi>Phlip</hi> 4.5 <hi>Let your Moderation be known unto all Men, the Lord is at hand.</hi> 6ly. It would rectifie your Judgment, of ſin, of Croſſes, yea, of things Temporal, Spiritual, and Eternal; Men in health living at diſtance from the thoughts of Death, Think otherwiſe of things, than in Sickneſs, and under the apprehenſion of Death. 7ly. It will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulat your affections you need be very ſober, the day is but ſhort <hi>Eccleſ,</hi> 1.9. The wiſe Man laughs at the young Man who Lets his heart Looſe Telling him, for all theſe things he wold come to Judgment 8ly. Believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoughts of Death, would beat back Temptations to ſin, Mortify dols and Luſts <hi>Job.</hi> 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.13.14. They would ſay, what ſhould I anſwer for this when the Lord riſeth up; It would make people quit boſom <hi>Dalilahs</hi> and Loſe pleaſure in them 1. The proud Man minding Death would account litle of being like <hi>Haman,</hi> the Second perſon in the Kingdom. 2ly. The covetous worldling entertaining believing thoughts of Death, would not be ſo much hunting after rents and profits, <hi>Judas</hi>-like ſelling their
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:62741:4"/>Maſter, <hi>Math.</hi> 26.16. He ſaid, <hi>what will you give me, and I will deliver him unto you, And they covenanted for Thrity peices of Silver;</hi> Nor like <hi>Demas</hi> who forſook Chriſt for the preſent world 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.10. 3ly. Beleiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoughts of Death would mortify pleaſures, and all vain delights, They would be als unſavory as the white of an Egg, the Harlot and drunken companion would be an ugly ſight; you would be convinced of the truth of that, That theſe pleaſurs Laſt but for a ſhort Seaſon, and leave a Laſting ſting behind them, <hi>Heb:</hi> 11.25. <hi>Prov:</hi> 23, 32 Yea be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leiving thoughts of Death, would make you double your diligence in your pace to heaven <hi>Eccle.</hi> 9.10. And quicken you to thoſe duties, heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenderneſs, and bitterneſs for ſin, as the Text points, <hi>Hezekiah wept</hi> ſore; It would make you earneſt in Self-examination 119. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 59.59 And inſtant in prayer <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.12. And would be a notable ſpurre to preparation for Death.</p>
            <p>Lay your account with it, Death is inevitable, and will not be put off as <hi>Dyvors</hi> puts off their Creditors, with fair words, flattery, Suſpenſions, Cautioury, flight; it will purſue, go where you will, nor will it bebrav'd out with a mans power and Station, and there is none can looſe Deaths Arrieſtment. Therefore wiſely reckon your time, and the ſhorteſt count is the beſt. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 90.12. <hi>Lord teach us to number our dayes that we may apply our hearts to wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom:</hi> There was a fool who reckoned on many years and had not a Night before him. <hi>Luk,</hi> 12, 20. But <hi>Job</hi> more wiſely reckoned Death a dayly door-neighbour, every day waiting his change, <hi>Job.</hi> 14.14 Know, that your holding here is not property, but Tennent-right, we ſhould alwayes be on a call; O make your reckoning and teſtament in time, <hi>Joſiah</hi> made a good Teſtament,, who turned to the Lord with all his Soul with all his heart, with all his might, according to all the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 23.25. &amp;c. <hi>David</hi> made a ſweet end who ſerved his Generation according to the will of God, and fell a ſleep in Chriſt. <hi>Acts.</hi> 13.36. Some great men have made an ill Teſtament, as <hi>Jehojakim</hi> who was buried with the burial of an Aſs. he lived undeſired and died unlamented, none to ſay, <hi>Ah Lord, or Ah his Glory, Jer,</hi> 22.18. &amp;c. There are ſome who dies and none to ſay, Woe is me for him, but that he is well away, and we are als well quit of him; their Memory Rots, and they are remembred with diſdain, <hi>Prov,</hi> 10.7. <hi>But the Memory of the just is bleſsed, and they ſhall be had in overlaſting remembrance, Pſal.</hi> 112.6. A good mans name never dyes, they will ſpeak good of him when he is dead; who cared little for him when he lived, they will ſpeak
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:62741:5"/>good of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Samuel</hi> now, who would have thought meanly of them had they lived in their days.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Herod</hi> that proud perſecutor, who ſlew <hi>James</hi> and put <hi>Peter</hi> in Priſon made an ill Teſtament, he ſwallowed down Impious Flatteries, and was eaten of Wormes or Lice, that he died, <hi>Act,</hi> 12, 2.3.23. Some have made an ill Teſtament at death, who have uſed Helliſh policy in their Life, as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> who deviſed to keep down and cruſhed the People of God, and would have had his Luſt ſatisfied on them. <hi>Exod.</hi> 1.10. and 15.9.</p>
            <p>I warne you great men who hear me, from the greateſt to the loweſt; many great men has dyed in <hi>Scotland</hi> within theſe ſixty years; Charity binds me up from ſpeaking of their eternal ſtate, ſome of them ſurvived their Honour, and went off the ſtage as the ſnuff of a Candle, your Honours will not go under the Turf with you: Many has darr'd and given defiance to death, that when that pale Horſe has looked them in the Face, and Conſcience awakened on them, changed Colours and quaked as <hi>Belſhazzer</hi> did <hi>Dan,</hi> 5.5. 6, You who are great men had need to walk ſo, as death be not terrible to you. 1, Becauſe few ſuch are called and ſaved. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1, 26 6. <hi>Not, many Noble,</hi> &amp;c. 2. Becauſe many great men will be ſore put to it at laſt <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.16.17. To cry to Mountains and Rocks, <hi>Fall on us and hide us from the face of him that ſitteth on the Throne, and from the wrath of the Lamb, for the great day of his Wrath is come, and who ſhall be able to ſtand;</hi> Many who hold their head very high now, Mighty men, and chief Captains may be put to it, and ſome who hears me this day, it may be their caſe.</p>
            <p>I warne <hi>Your Grace,</hi> and my Noble Lords, and much Honoured <hi>Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> take heed what you do, the judgment is the Lords; there be few Parliaments but ſome Members dye in the time, or ſhortly after, God knows within a few dayes where ſome of you will Land for Etemity: I remember within theſe thirty four years, of one who rode in Pomp to Parliament but warmed not his Seat, was hurried to his Lodging, took bed, and his Sun ſet in a dark and ſtormy cloud, he was a principal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triver of the overthrow of the Work of Reformation in <hi>Scotland.</hi> Take heed what you do or deſign, you muſt all dye and compear 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.10. As the word is, Be manifeſted, diſcovered, laid open, your deeds your intentions, your Cabin-Counſells, there will be no palliating of foul things with fair Colours.</p>
            <p>I will tell you to whom Death will be terrible, and why, 1. It will be terrible to them who have not their aggreement made with God, not found in peace, Them God will meet as an enemy. 2ly. Theſe who has not
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:62741:5"/>repented and obeyed the Goſpel, As the fooliſh Virgins <hi>Math,</hi> 25. Chriſt threatens the <hi>Jews</hi> they ſhould dye in their ſins unrepented of <hi>John</hi> 8.24. 3ly. Who ly down in the duſt and their bones full of the ſins of their youth, <hi>Job,</hi> 20 11. 4. Who dye in unbelief, to ſuch, God ſwears they ſhall not enter in his reſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 95.11. 5. Who have not their work perfect before God, but reſts in an empty name and profeſſion. <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.1.2. 6. The backſlider in heart, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.38. 7. Theſe who hears the word and does it not, <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.26. 8. Who ſets their neſt on high, as the fool, who ſaid, he had much goods laid up for many years. <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.19. 9: The perſecuter and contemner of Gods People, as <hi>Nabal.</hi> 2. <hi>Sam,</hi> 25.10.38. 10. Theſe who dye under the plague of a hard heart as <hi>Pharaoh. Exod.</hi> 14. 11. Death is terrible to theſe who are ſelf Cheaters and Deceivers, who cries peace, peace, when ſudden deſtruction is at the door. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.3. 12. Who dyes neither to be deſired of God nor man. as <hi>Jehoram.</hi> 2 <hi>Chron,</hi> 21.20. 13. Theſe who dye embracing Idolatry as <hi>Ahaz.</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 28.22. He Treſpaſſed yet more againſt God, and Sacrificed to the Gods of <hi>Damaſcus.</hi> 14. Theſe who dies without the experimental knowledge of theſe three. 1. Without the knowledge of Converſion, except one be converted he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not enter into the Kingdom of Heaven. <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.3. 2. Without the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of Holineſs, without which no man, if he were a King, ſhall ſee the Face of God in mercy. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.14. 3. Without ſome knowledg and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of their eternal lodging. 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.12. I <hi>know in whom</hi> I <hi>have believed</hi> ſays <hi>Paul,</hi> I <hi>know of a houſe not made with hands,</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1.</p>
            <p>Queſt. But why will Death be terrible to ſuch? Anſ. Becauſe then they will get no deſire granted; not a drop of cold Water to cool the Tongue, <hi>Luke.</hi> 16 24. The rich Glutton could not obtain that mean requeſt 2. Then their Carnal propes and confidences are battered down, their hope gives up the Ghoſt. <hi>Job.</hi> 11, 20. 3. Becauſe then God will be terrible to them, He will meet them as a <hi>Boar</hi> bereaved of her Whelps, and rent the Caul of their heart, and devour them as a Lyon <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 13.8. <hi>Conſider, this you that forget God, leaſt he tear you in pieces when none ſhall deliver. Pſal.</hi> 50 22. 4 Becauſe then, fear and loſs comes at once, and there is no hope, that their caſe will mend.</p>
            <p>Now, would you have death not to be a terrour, but a comfort to you, Then 1. Look to it through the righteouſneſs of Chriſt, who takes away the Sting, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.55. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 2 Be <hi>Zions</hi> friend, and her King Chriſts friend, and embrace him as thy Souls Beloved, and his terms of peace preſcribed. 3. Look on Death as the Veſſel, that will take thee off this troubleſome
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:62741:6"/>Sea to thy eternal reſt. 4. Look on death as Chriſt ſpeaks of it, <hi>Our Friend Lazarus ſleepeth, John</hi> 11.11. 5. Look to it in the promiſe of his preſence, Who will be with thee when thou goes thorow the dark valley, <hi>Pſal,</hi> 23.4.</p>
            <p n="6">6, Look on Death as thy God's Servant, that dare not touch thee, but as thy God will. 7. Be prepared for it: Are you ready, and your Lamps Trimmed? I fear the Eccho of conſcence in ſome, is, I am yet to Learn this Great Leſſon.</p>
            <p>Conſider theſe things, 1. <hi>Wiſhes</hi> and <hi>would</hi> be's will not be taken off your hand, <hi>Balaam</hi> a Stranger to God, wiſhed to dye the Death of the Righteous <hi>Numb.</hi> 23.10, O Says the man I would fain be Godly, Thou wilt not come to a Bleſſed end if thou get no more. Says Chriſt Bleſſed is the man whom his Lord finds ſo doing <hi>Matth,</hi> 24, 46. Not ſo wiſhing that he had been better. 2. Many meet with Death before they be ready, what knows thou, if thou get time at Death; What if the Lord anſwer thee as <hi>Judges</hi> 10.13. Go to the Gods whom you have ſerved; Shall I take the worlds, the devils, your Luſts, and ſins Leavings? 3. Conſider you may be confuſed at Death; It's harder to dye well than is imagined, Death will try to purpoſe your Graces, duties, and enjoyments; you have need to be buſie, and be as buſie as you can, you will have enough to do, to win to patience and aſſurance. 4. Mind as Death leaves you, Judgement will find you; You will not dye twice, if ſo you might take a venture, Therefore deferr not preparation, which is of univerſall and Greateſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment; If peace of conſcience, To dye with comfort, To have the Soul bound up in the bundel of life, be of concernment, Then preparation for Death is of concernment; If eternall well and woe; to eſcape hell, and come to Heaven, be of concernment, Then is preparation for Death of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt,</hi> But wherein conſiſts this preparation? <hi>Anſ:</hi> 1. In laying up a ſtore, a good foundation for the time to come 1 <hi>Tim:</hi> 6.19. To be wiſe as the <hi>Ant,</hi> that provides in Summer for the Winter ſtorm <hi>Prov.</hi> 6.8.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To live a Righteous holy life, the life of a wreſtler with God as <hi>Jacob Gen:</hi> 32. The life of walking with God, as <hi>Enoch Gen:</hi> 15. The life of Self<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denyed-obedience, as <hi>Abrabam Heb:</hi> 11.8. He went on a call, not knowing whether, and the life of a pilgrim and ſtranger, Deſiring a Heavenly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.13.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It conſiſts. in having the Heart Sequeſtrat from Luſts, Idols, and Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture injoyments, Crucifyed to the world, and the luſts and affections there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of <hi>Gal:</hi> 5.24.6.14.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:62741:6"/>
            <p n="4">4. In being on the watch-tower <hi>Pſal.</hi> 130. <hi>Luk</hi> 12.37, Bleſſed are thoſe Servants whom the Lord when he cometh ſhall find watching.</p>
            <p n="5">5. In having Graces in Lively exerciſe, Faith ready for Viſion, and Hope for poſſeſſion.</p>
            <p n="6">6. In having thy peace within between God and thy Soul ſecured, the Spirit witneſſing with your Spirits that you are the Sons of God. <hi>Rom.</hi> 16</p>
            <p n="7">7. In dying in the Lord, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.13. Found in Chriſt <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.9. Unit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to Chriſt <hi>John.</hi> 17.23. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in them, and thou in me; Commiting the Soul to him as a God of truth <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31.5, Truſting Chriſt as a ſafe Veſſel to to carry the through.</p>
            <p>O what an excellent Death is it, to dye in the Faith of theſe Six things 1. That thou are Elected, called, adopted, juſtified, and he is thy God, and that thy name is Written in the Lambs Book of life, And thou has no more to doe, but ſay, Father in thy hands I commend my Spirit, as ſaid Chriſt <hi>Luke</hi> 23.46,</p>
            <p n="2">2. To dye in the Faith of this, that all his dealings to thee in thy life, have been Mercy and truth, and for good <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.10 and thou wilt not queſtion his favours; To dye in the Faith of this, that thy Works have been accepted, and to ſay with old <hi>Simeon Now lets thou thy Servant depart in peace, for mine Eyer have ſeen thy Salvation Luk</hi> 2.29.</p>
            <p n="3">3. To dye in the faith of the promiſed Glory, and of the out making of all the promiſes, that thou can ſay as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 17.15. <hi>When I awake I ſhall ſee his face in Righteouſnes, and be ſatisfied as with the likneſs of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. To Dye in the Faith of this, That Chriſt hath taken away the Sting of Death, and thou haſt intereſt in his Victories, over Death, Hell, Sin, and the Grave, and that he will be with thee, and meaſure out thy pain, and make all thy Bed in Thy Sickneſs.</p>
            <p n="5">5. To Dye in the Faith, That God will viſit his Church, as did <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph Gen.</hi> 50.24.25.</p>
            <p n="6">6. To Dye in the Faith, That all the enemies of his Glory ſhall be brought down, and his Kingdom ſhall be exalted.</p>
            <p>Death will give people experience of theſe five things, Of the Vanity of the World, of the Truth of the Word, of the Bitterneſs of Sin, of the Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribleneſs of falling in the hands of the living God, and of the Sweetneſs of Gods Service to them that ſhall reſt from their Labours.</p>
            <p>Many Dye with ſtrong Terrours, not prepared, and ſome Stupid, ly down with a Lye in their Right-hand <hi>Iſai:</hi> 44.20. And yet are ſaid to Dye like Lambs; They are like a Man put out at the window of a high Tower
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:62741:7"/>in a Dark-night, and falls in a deep Ditch, ſad is his Wakning.</p>
            <p>Happy are they who are ready, Willing, and deſirous to Dye. 1, There is a Childiſh deſire of Death, like <hi>Achab,</hi> who would Dy in a pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t for <hi>Naboths</hi> Vineyard 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 21.4. 2. A paſſionat deſire like <hi>Jonahs</hi> for the Gourds withering <hi>Jonah</hi> 4.8. 3. A Rebellious deſire, like that of the <hi>Iſaraelites Numb.</hi> 14, 2. 4, A ſolid and Judicious deſire, That is attended 1 with diligence in every duty, knowing that ſhortly wee muſt put off this Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.14. 2. With laying up a ſtore that wee may be accepted of him 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.19. 3 With a conſtant waiting for a change <hi>Job</hi> 14.14. Trimming the Lamps, and girding up the Loyns with the wiſe Virgins, <hi>Math.</hi> 25.4. 4 With the knowledge of their Well being after Death 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1. <hi>Wee know if our earthly houſe of this Tabernacle were diſſolved, Wee have a building with God, an houſe not made with hands; eternal in the Heavens.</hi> 5. It's attended with an heart deadneſs to things here-away uſing the World as if wee uſed it not, becauſe time is ſhort 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.29.31. O for ſuch grounds of deſire.</p>
            <p>The ſecond thing I would ſpeak to, is, That who would expect favour at Death, would ſtudy Uprightneſs. 1. There is a Moral Uprightneſs in reference to Mens Actions, which a Graceleſs Man like <hi>Abimeleh</hi> may have by reſtraint <hi>Gen.</hi> 20.2. an Evangelical Uprightneſs, that ſets the Eye and Heart God-ward, which is not an Act, but a Gracious frame and habit, wrought in the Heart, which is the chief ſeat of it; Hypocriſy is like a paint that only colours the Skin, This is God's Work, for no Man can make his Heart clean <hi>Prov.</hi> 20.9. It fits the Soul to walk with, and ſerve God in the right manner, and to deſign the Lords Glory as the main end; The upright Man knows no other fountain of Mercy but God's Grace, and no end of duty but God's Glory.</p>
            <p>For confirming the point. 1. It is the paremptor will of God, which is the higheſt of Reaſons: God remits from the firſt Covenant with <hi>Adam</hi> of abſolute perſonal perfection but requires a ſecond Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant perfection <hi>Gen:</hi> 17. 1, Uprightneſs, Truth in the inward parts <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.6. Which is the higheſt Believers can attain while on Earth. 2. It is highly well pleaſing to God 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.17. I know O Lord, ſaith <hi>David,</hi> thou takes pleaſure in Uprightneſs; O how well pleaſed was <hi>Chriſt</hi> with <hi>Nathaniel</hi> an Iſraelite indeed in whom there was no guile <hi>John</hi> 1.47. His countenance doth behold the upright <hi>Pſal.</hi> 11.7. they get a good look of God; Wee ſhould imitat Chriſt if wee would do what delights God <hi>John,</hi> 8.29. He did alwayes thoſe things that pleaſed his father, who has no pleaſure in ſin <hi>Pſal.</hi> 5, 4.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, This is the great and characteriſtical diſtinction
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:62741:7"/>that puts a difference between the Saint and Hypocrite in point of duties, as between the Publican and the Phariſee <hi>Luk.</hi> 18. Between <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Abel Gen.</hi> 4.4. It is that without which a man cannot be a true Chriſtian, under the higheſt profeſſion, and with which a man is a true Chriſtian with Leſs profeſſion; It is the very ſtandart of every Grace and duty, Grace without it, is but hypocriſy, and duty without it is but iniquity: A Saint cannot want it to Seaſon all his Graces and duties, it qualifies all, It's like the blood that runs through all the veins, the very life of the Chriſtian 1. Faith moſt be unfeigned 1 <hi>Tim,</hi> 1.5, There werea ſort of people ſeemed to truſt in God, but were not ſincere, they thought not as they ſpoke the Lord could not abide them <hi>Pſal,</hi> 78.35.36.37. 2. Repentance muſt be ſound, the Lord challenges feigned turning to him <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.10. Wee have need to pray, Lord wiſh our Teares from hypocriſy.</p>
            <p n="3">3, Love to God muſt be ſincere, or elſs wee are curſed <hi>Eph:</hi> 6, 24, 1. <hi>Cor:</hi> 16.22. There were ſome who pretended great reſpect to God, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertook fair <hi>Jer.</hi> 42, 2.3.6.20.21. but ſtood not by it, they were falſe diſſemblers in their hearts, they never kept a word. <hi>Jer.</hi> 44.16. They down right gave themſelves the Lye, and declared they would not do as they had ſaid. 4. Love to our neighbour muſt be ſincere, wee muſt love him <hi>with a pure Heart fervently</hi> 1. <hi>Pet,</hi> 1.22 5. Prayer to God muſt be ſincere 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2, 8. Wee muſt lift up pure hands. 6, preaching muſt be as of fincerity, in the ſight of God 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.17. In a word wee have ſo much grace in good earneſt, as we have ſincerity, and no more. Laſt reaſon none. elſe can expect Heavens glory, and who wants Hope of Heaven cannot dye with comfort <hi>Math.</hi> 5.8. <hi>Bleſſed are the pure in heart, they ſhall ſee God. Pſal.</hi> 140.13. The upright, and only ſuch, ſhall dwell in his preſence <hi>Pſal.</hi> 15.1.2, Only theſe who walk uprightly, ſhall dwell in his holy Hill, With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Faith, repentance, love, we cannot be ſaved <hi>John.</hi> 3, 18. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13 <hi>Luk.</hi> 13.3 And without uprightnes we have none of theſe; All depends on this one thing, both in point of preſent comfort, and everlaſting happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs without this, the ſoul is loſt when we have done all we can.</p>
            <p>There is great need to try it, for both Sincerity and Hypocriſy lyes deep in the heart, &amp; both may be over-looked: A Gracious Soul may be I ealous he wants it on miſtakes 1. Becauſe of decays in Grace; To remove this, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider 1. <hi>Peter</hi> had his decayes, yet his heart was right in the main, a while wee are here the beſt have ſome remainders of corruption to moleſt them. There is none perfect <hi>Rom,</hi> 7.20. Honeſt <hi>Paul</hi> complains of an ill Neighbour. Sin dwelling in him. 3. a decay may be apprehended, and appear to be where it
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:62741:8"/>is not, there may be a growing at the root in humility, as in winter, the ſap goes to the root of the tree, and keeps life in it,</p>
            <p n="2">2. Some queſtion their uprightneſs becauſe of Severe rods, <hi>Thy witneſſes are againſt me</hi> ſaith <hi>Job,</hi> 10.17. I anſwer, this were to queſtion that Gold were Gold, becauſe put in the fire to be refined and purged of its droſs, the beſt Saint on earth has ſome droſs of corruption to be purged away by the Croſs <hi>Iſai.</hi> 27.9 In heaven the Saint is all Grace and no ſin, in hell the ſinners is all ſin and no Grace.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Some Iealous their ſincerity becauſe of diſtracting vain thoughts in duty, I anſwer, this is dangerous, for thus you condemne the generation of the righteous; There ſhould be none ſincere on earth, if this did hold; There be none who wants theſe; but are theſe thoughts thy burden, art thou ſtriving againſt them, and hates them <hi>Pſal,</hi> 119.113. Thou does not cheriſh them, Its well.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Say ſome, my Self-love fears me: I Anſwer there is a Self-love in Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordination to the Glory of God, whereby a man aims in the firſt place at God's glory, and then his own happineſs, That is Lawful. There is again a ſelf-love in competition wherein a man regards <hi>Self</hi> more then God's glory, that is unlawfull, and a ground of Jealouſie when a man puts himſelfe in Gods room.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> For trial 1. The upright man his great work is about his heart to purge it, He knows ſin in the heart is worſe than ſin in the life: Sin in the life may proceed from weakneſs of grace, ſin in the heart from ſtrength of corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>Pſal.</hi> 66.18. If I regaird inquity in my heart no hearing of prayer. There be two things the Sincere looks moſt to, His God that he may be Honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and his heart that it may be reformed; Hypocrits are moſt upon out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, and juſtifies their hearts by venture. The upright man neglects not his outward work, he knows as to neglect the heart argues Hypocriſy, ſo to neglect the life argues profanity; He looks to both, but moſt to the heart.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The upright Man has a two-fold univerſality, one as to ſin, another as to duty. 1. For ſin, his heart is carried out againſt all ſin, ſecret as well as open becauſe it is againſt the Lord, as <hi>Joſpeh Gen.</hi> 39, 9. and <hi>David Pſal:</hi> 1912, The hypocrits fails here, he refrains from ſin obvious to the world only, The upright man ſets himſelf againſt ſmall ſins as well as great; It's true as ſin is againſt God, and his holy Law, there is no ſin ſmall, but there are degrees of ſins, the upright man ſetts himſelfe againſt his own ſin, his predominant, The ſin of his conſtitution <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18.23. Yea, he hates every falſe way <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.104. There be ſome goes over the belly of known acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:62741:8"/>principles intheir ſin; Some ſay a man ſhould not commit adultery, who will commit adultery, ſome will abhore Idols, that will commit Sacrilege <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.22. Some will abhore ſwearing, Thieft, whoredome, who will debauch time and perſon with tipling and drunkenneſs, this is to be guilty of the Breach of the whole Law, becauſe it is a deſpiſing that authority that is ſtamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on all the commands <hi>Jam:</hi> 2.10, 11,</p>
            <p n="2">2. The upright man his heart is carried out to all duty, to eſteem all Gods commands concerning all things to be right <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.128, To have a good Conſcience in all things <hi>Heb:</hi> 13, 18, Who obeyes one command for Gods ſake will obey what ever he commands,</p>
            <p n="3">3. Uprightneſs preſſes the Mans heart to reach the higheſt attainments of Grace, the hypocrites obedience is ſtinted, but <hi>Paul</hi> forgets things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind and preſſes forward <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.12.13.14.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The upright Man baulks no duty for ſuffering, ſome come out of Great tribulation waſhing their Garments in the Blood of the Lamb, <hi>Rev.</hi> 7, 14.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> 1. For exhortation, O Study uprightneſs 1 Becauſe its rare, and ill looked on in the world, <hi>Micah.</hi> 7, 2, there are none upright among men. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 12, 1, The faithfull fails from among the Childeren of men <hi>Job,</hi> 12, 4. The juſt upright Man is laughed to ſcorne; It is for a Lamentation, that ſincere Soules are thin ſown in this generation, if there be any more ſincere than another, they are like the ſpeckled bird <hi>Jer.</hi> 12.9. That all the birds of the Field gazeth on <hi>Iſaiah.</hi> 8.18. <hi>I</hi> and the Children whom the Lord has given me, are for ſigns and wonders in Iſrael, the World cannot abide ſuch <hi>Prov.</hi> 29, 27, <hi>He that is upright in his way is an abomination to the wicked;</hi> So much the more ſtudy uprightnes. 2. Conſider there is nograce like it, and no grace without it, it denominats a man a Chriſtian, and a Bleſſed man <hi>Pſal</hi> 119.1. 3. It gives confidence before the Lord in prayer 1 <hi>John</hi> 3 21. <hi>Prov.</hi> 15.8. The prayer of the upright is his delight, ſuch are wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come to God in their adreſſes, that is a Rich Bleſſing <hi>Jâm</hi> 4.8. 4. Such ſhall be made glad and Glory in the Lord, who are upright in their hearts <hi>Pſal</hi> 64.10. 5. The Upright Man ſhall keep his feet when falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood will fail <hi>Prov.</hi> 10 9 He walks ſurely <hi>Iſai</hi> 28 17. The refuge of Lyes ſhall be ſweeped away, the Upright may have many Enemies, but God Almighty is on his ſide <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.1. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55.16.18. Many are with me ſays <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> they ſhall get their feet on the Neck of all their Enemies <hi>Pſal.</hi> 49.14, The Upright ſhall have dominion in the Morning. 6, Uprightneſs ſupplies
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:62741:9"/>many defects, when one can appeal to God anent the ſincerity of his Heart as <hi>Paul</hi> did <hi>Acts</hi> 23.1.7. The Upright have room in the Saints Prayers <hi>Pſal.</hi> 125.4. <hi>Do good O Lord to them that be good, to them who are up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right in their hearts.</hi> 8. Sincerity Crowns all Grace with perſeverence, Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſy withers, ſincerity holds out in the worſt of times, like the good ground, It's fruitful notwithſtanding of ſcorching heat, <hi>Luke</hi> 8.15.9. Without this all duties are a Lye <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.34. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> They prayed and flate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red God, and Lyed with their Mouth, for their Heart was not right with God. 10. The upright man has comfort in the greateſt Extremity and ſtorm of his Life, a boſome friend: <hi>Paul,</hi> when he had the ſentence of Death againſt himſelf and others, ſaid, this is our rejoycing, the Teſtimony of our conſcience, that in ſimplicity and Godly ſincerity we have had our Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation in the World 2 <hi>Cor:</hi> 1, 9, 12. This makes the Man's Face to ſhine, and makes quietneſs within <hi>Prov.</hi> 14.14, Whereas an ill conſcience is like a gnawing worm, a heavy load above a burden. Then ſincerity gives comfort in the laſt Extremity of Death, <hi>Mark the perſect, behold the upright the end of that man is peace,</hi> tho' he Dye in Warr <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.37. O that is ſweet when the Heart does not reproach in a Dying-hour <hi>Job</hi> 27.6. and God not a terrour to the Man. Laſtly that Man has intereſt in that promiſe, that's of a wide compaſs <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84.11, <hi>The Lord God is a Son and a ſhield,</hi> to direct Comfort and defend, he will give Grace and Glory, and withold no good thing from him that walks uprightly.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> How ſhall wee win to this lovely deſirable thing? 1 Be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced of heart unfoundnes, make an errand to God for it <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.80. <hi>Let my Heart be Sound in thy ſtatuts. Pſal</hi> 51.10, <hi>Creat O Lord in me a clean heart</hi> a ſtudy much the attributes of God, eſpecialy his omniſciency <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.12.13. <hi>All things are vaked &amp; open before him with whom we have to doe</hi> keep God in your Eye, that is injoined <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.1 <hi>Walk beſor me and be upright;</hi> This keeped <hi>Joſeph</hi> right <hi>Gen,</hi> 39.9. You will never prove ſteel to the back if God be out of ſight; this keeped <hi>David</hi> right <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16, 8, &amp; 25.15. Keep upon your hearts the perſwaſion of his Alſeeing-Eye, what makes many ſo unſtable, they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get God, 3, keep Heaven in your Eye, this keeped <hi>Moſes</hi> right amidſt many temptations and ſnares, he had reſpect to the recompence of reward <hi>Heb,</hi> 11, 26. This keeped <hi>Paul</hi> right, that he fainted not, he minded the exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and eternal weight of Glory 2 <hi>Cor:</hi> 4, 16, 17, You will faint and give over if your Hearts be faſtned on things that are ſeen, you will take to the neareſt ſhore, ſo has been ſeen of an apoſtat generation.</p>
            <p>The laſt branch of the point, they who would have comfort in Death, muſt
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:62741:9"/>have a Religious walk in their Life, and do what is good in the Lords ſight Walking is a progreſſive motion, not like that of the door on the hinges that moves oft, but goes not foreward.</p>
            <p>Conſider theſe things for clearing this point, 1. Wee are commanded to walk in the Lords way, and that conſtantly <hi>Deut.</hi> 19.9. Walk ever in his ways. 2. The Saints have reſolved this as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119, 112, and are injoyned to make inquiry after the Lords way for this end <hi>Jer.</hi> 6.16.3. The Lord commends thoſe who make conſcience of their walk, as <hi>Zachari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth Luk.</hi> 1.6. Whoſe commendation will never die. 4. The Lord threatens them ſore who looks not to their walk <hi>Jer.</hi> 9.14. <hi>Lev:</hi> 26.21. &amp;c. he will heat the furnace ſeven times more for them. 5. It is one of the precious promiſes of the New Covenant, that the Lord will give us his ſpirit to cauſe us walk in his way, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.27. 6. The Lord calls for it as a chief evidence of a Souls ſenſe of Kindneſs that wee walk humbly with our God, <hi>Mitah.</hi> 6.8. 7. The Lord's people ſenſible of kindneſs have iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged thenſelves to this <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.12, <hi>&amp;c. What ſhall I render to the Lord? I will walk before the Lord.</hi> 8. You will find the Lord quarrels no people ſo much for their words as for their walk <hi>Deut.</hi> 5.28.29. They had well ſpoken, O! ſays the Lord, that there were ſuch a heart in them to fear me, and keep all my Commandements, the Man is only bleſſed in his deed. <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.25. Many are ſtrangers to a Chriſtian Walk. 1. ſome will not ſo much as give God fair words for all his favours, but Sacrifices to their own Net <hi>Hab.</hi> 1.16. 2. Some complement God in words, and little af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected in their hearts <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106.12.13. They ſung his Praiſe but ſoon for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got his Works, and waited not for his Counſel. 3. Some with ſome kind of ſenſe will commend God in words, who never came the length of a Chriſtian Walk; profeſs they know God, and in Works deny him. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1, 16, theſe are Self-cheaters.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion,</hi> Why are moſt people pleaſed with a profeſſion without a Chriſtian walk, 1, From Ignorance of God, as if he would be put off with fair words and bare acknowledgment, this is a mocking of God. 2 It flows from undervaluing of his Mercies, as if they were worth no more. 3. Becauſe there is not ſo much difficulty in profeſſion and words, as in a walk; It is Grace that muſt diſpoſe to this, the Devil cares not how much you complement God with Words, if the heart be not toward God, and your walk commend you not to him.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As ever you would ſhew a ſenſe of the Lord's kindneſs in your life, and expect his kindneſs at Death make conſcience of a Religious walk: I
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:62741:10"/>preſs it with theſe Arguments. 1. It is your Chriſtian walk that will put to ſilence the ignorance of fooliſh men and convince others 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.15. 2. Its the walk that will beſt ſecure peace of conſcience in the worſt of times <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.165. <hi>Great peace have they which love thy Law: and nothing ſhall affend them.</hi> 3. It is your walk that will keep the paſſage open to God in all your neceſſities, the man is barr'd out who hears and does not, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.31. he will not be inquired of ſuch, but ſet his face againſt them <hi>Ezek.</hi> 14.2.8. The ſlanderer and Adulterer what ever he profeſs, he is not wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come to God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50, 16, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 4. It is your walk that will difference you from the World, not a common gift or profeſſion <hi>Luk,</hi> 18 In theſe a Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e may go beyond a Gracious Man. 5. There is nothing ſweeter for a Man to reflect on when the Eye-ſtrings are breaking, than for a Man to have that to ſay, that he has Exerciſed himſelf always to keep a Conſcience void of offence toward God and Man in his walk, and in this <hi>Hezekiah</hi> had ground of Comfort, but it was not the ground of his Conſidence; that was placed in Chriſts Righteouſneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> 2. I would offer theſe things by way of Advice. 1. If you would walk ſo as to commend God, and expect comfort at Death, ſet your Face to the right Airt to <hi>Zion Jer.</hi> 50.5. To Glorify God in all your Actings. 2. Have your Salvation much in your Eye, as preferable to all things, Many forget they have immortal Souls; all their care is for things below Heaven. 3. Study much acquaintance with the word as the Rule <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.16. He that walks according to that Rule, peace ſhall be upon him and Mercy, as upon thee <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God. 4. Eye Chriſt much as your patern and abſolute copy 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.6. Walk as he alſo walked. 5. Look farther than Grace within <hi>Pſal.</hi> 71.16. ſaith <hi>David I will go in the strength of the Lord God;</hi> you will miſcarry if you take on upon your own heads. 6. Be oft taking account of your ſelf, that you may better recover a loſt ſtep <hi>Hag.</hi> 1.7. Conſider your ways <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.59. <hi>I thought upon my ways, and turned my feet to thy testimonies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> 3 There be ſeven ſort of people reprovable. 1. Theſe who walk in black Ignorance and have no perſwaſion of things in their own minds, only receive ſuch and ſuch things from cuſtom or practice of others, theſe cannot keep a ſtraight courſe. 2. The prophane carnal walker <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.27. The <hi>Philiſtines</hi> were aſhamed of what the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> did; Wee are all ſhamed in this Generation, and Heathens if they were among us, would be aſhamed of us: How many of all Ranks, walks in Drunkeneſs, Lying, Swearing, Whoredome, Sabbath-breaking, Living a Prayerleſs Life
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:62741:10"/>bringing forth the Fruits of Atheiſm, which excluds people out of Heaven and brings on the wrath of God 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.9.10. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.6. I am affraid there is a ſtorm of Wrath and Vengance coming on the Land, if matters mend not, if Mercy and Repentance prevent not. 3. Some are inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat in their walk, ſome miſtake, placing all their Religion in Zeal, and it may be baſtard Zeal without knowledge, people nor knowing what ſpirit they are of, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.2. <hi>Luk.</hi> 9.55. and ſuch have a kind of heart abhorrence of pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, others place too much in prudence, and gives no kindly way to Zeal, ſuch will not commend God, nor are on their guard againſt Temptations and Snares. 4. Some conſult more their wit than their conſcience, in all their actings, but it is not right if conſcience have not a vote in the matter, ſuch will go a black gate readily in an hour of Temptation, and ſo at length be taken in their own craftineſs 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.19. 5. The timerous walker, altho' he have good inclinations and meanings, yet he is eaſily ſcarred from the moſt neceſſary duties <hi>Prov.</hi> 29.25. the fear of man is a ſnare, ſuch will make a Slave of their Conſcience, and lay their Soul in pawn to reſcue themſelves from danger. 6. the unconſtant walker will never Glorify God, all his Religion lies in ſtarts, his Goodneſs wears off like the Morning Cloud and early Dew, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 6.4. 7. The Lazy Chriſtian, who makes no progreſs, going from ſtrength to ſtrength <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84.7. The motion of ſome is ſo ſlow that it is hard to gueſs whether they be bound for Heaven or Hell; Be more ſerious and diligent.</p>
            <p>I know not how you will take it, but if ever your Religion paſs current before God, Its your walk will bear the ſtreſs of its commendation.</p>
            <p>I would add a few things ſhortly by way of Caution, in reference to your walk 1. Beware you be not in League with any known Sin, Unmortified Luſts, unrepented of Idols, you will never have a day to do well if you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard Iniquity in your Heart, for then you have no acceſs to God <hi>Pſal.</hi> 66.18. 2. Beware of misbehaving to the ſpirit of God, by whoſe influence and aſſiſtance alone, you can move in the way of God, Tempt him not as <hi>Annantas</hi> and <hi>Saphira</hi> did <hi>Act.</hi> 5.9. Vex him not as theſe Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous perſons did, who made God turn their Enemy <hi>Iſai,</hi> 63.10 Reſiſt him not as theſe ſtiff-naked, and uncircumciſed in heart did, <hi>Act.</hi> 7.51. Quench not his motions 1 <hi>Theſs:</hi> 5, 19. Grieve him not <hi>Eph:</hi> 4, 30, if you adventure thus to miſcarry, you will not ſtep a right ſtep. 3. Beware of needleſs, familiar, frequent haunt and converſe with perſons perverſe in principles, that you receive not of their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lagues, <hi>Rev,</hi> 18, 4, and with perſons perverſe in practices, that you learn no their ways, and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:62741:11"/>get a ſnare to your Souls <hi>Prov:</hi> 22, 24, 25, For bold adventures in this has been the ruine of this Generation, <hi>Prov:</hi> 13.20. A companion of fools ſhall be deſtroyed: You may have a bad Acquaintance and Relation to whom you muſt no ways miſ-behave by incivility, and you may buy and ſell with a <hi>Turk,</hi> But touch with them in a point as a ball on a plain that ſoon rolls off, but chuſe no wicked Companion. 4. See that you be not glutted with exceſſive Love of the World, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2, 15, <hi>If any man love the World, the love of the Father is not in him;</hi> This Love and exceſſive care of the World, ſtiffles and choaks good motions <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.22, As it was with the young man in the Goſpel <hi>Matth:</hi> 19 22, And <hi>Demas</hi> imbracing the preſent World, turned his back upon the way of God 2 <hi>Tim:</hi> 4.10. if you advert not to theſe things, you can never walk in truth and with a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect heart.</p>
            <p>I would addreſſe my ſelfe to this Honourable Court; I know not if ever I ſhall preach more, or ſome of you hear more, 1. You have many Eyes of men on earth on you, and his Eyes that are like a flam of fire <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.14, 2. You bear a great figure by office, called <hi>Gods Pſal.</hi> 82, 1, and <hi>Fathers</hi> to the people <hi>Gen.</hi> 45, 8, <hi>Iſai</hi> 45, 19, and many other ſtiles of great import, 3. God ſeverely threatens Magiſtrats if they misbehave, who are neither above inſtruction, nor without correction, if they fail <hi>Job,</hi> 12, 21, <hi>He poures contempt upon Princes,</hi> and weakens the ſtrength of the mighty. 4. You are lyable to many difficulties and dangers, which many ſee not, who will readily obſerve your defects, 5. Your task is great, to hear the plaints of the poore, to repreſſe the inſolencie of the proud, and Miniſter juſtice to all. Altho' God has exalted you above others, you are ſervants to Subjects to watch for their well <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1. 2. Therefore take heed, beware, 1. Of unſeaſonable undue contendings, that ye con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume not one another <hi>Gal.</hi> 5, 15, unite in what is true and good 2. Beware of Tyrranny and oppreſſion, <hi>Fathers</hi> of the republick, ſhould not provoke people to wrath, no more nor Natural Parents ſhould provoke their Children <hi>Eph.</hi> 6, 4.9, No mans power on earth is abſolut, but Limited, Kings muſt have revenues to put them in better capacity <hi>Ezra.</hi> 4 13, And they ſhould have more in time of warre than in time of peace, then our Hearts muſt be inlarged without grudge, to make a liberal offering; better venter much then Loſſe all: I hope the Lord will help this Honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Court, to ſhun what may grind the faces of the poore, and what is heavy to widows and Fatherleſs, or may break credit in the Nation, but none will miſconſtruct to require what tends to the honour of <hi>the King,</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:62741:11"/>to whom we ow ſo much, and ſeeks nothing for himſelfe, but what is for the ſafty and ſecurity of the Nation 3, Beware of pride, and upliftedneſs of Spirit, which overthrew <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and <hi>Haman.</hi> 4, Beware of perſons, and things that may prove dangerous to Kirk, or State. 5, Bewarre of Crudulity, try before you truſt that ye be not impoſed on, <hi>Sathan</hi> may borrow <hi>Peters</hi> Tongue to give <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ad advice to his Maſter <hi>Matth.</hi> 16, 22, 6 Beware of Self-ſeeking, the plague of the gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, it's a brand of infamy, eſpecialy in Great men, where it is, it's a deep Large gulf, in which ſome Mens motions all center, as did <hi>Judas,</hi> who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed Chriſt, and <hi>Pilat's,</hi> who to pleaſe the people, and gratify <hi>Ceſar,</hi> crucified Chriſt, over the Belly of his Concience, and warning of his wife; He made a foul hinder end; We have oft ſmarted by men of that temper: We may cry out as its in <hi>Phil.</hi> 2, 21, <hi>All Seek their own things, not the things which are Jeſus Chriſis.</hi> ſuch, whatever fruit they bring forth, being to <hi>Selfe</hi> they are reckoned empty <hi>Hos:</hi> 10, 1, There be three ill pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties ſome have, which come all to one, <hi>Time-ſerving, Man-pleaſing, Self-ſeeking;</hi> A Self-ſeeker will ſerve the humor of any time, whom he harraſſes this year, he will carreſſe the next, if the wind blow ſo, and it may ſerve a turne He will ſtudy to pleaſe men (to the venture of his Soul) if they command him this day to doe, he is ready, and if the nex day, to undo, he is alwayes at command, ſuch are not unlike that <hi>Ruſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Eccleſiaſtick in <hi>England,</hi> of whom its ſtoried, <hi>he would ſtand with all, but fall with none,</hi> As Proteſtant or Papiſt had the aſcendant, accordingly he moved, and when asked, how he came to ſtand ſo? He anſwered, he keept ſtill one principle, and that was to hold his Living.</p>
            <p>I would adviſe you to theſe things in your walk. 1. Labour for a good foreſight in things, be not head ſtrong in what may endanger, As <hi>David</hi> in an humour, would number the People, 2 <hi>Sam,</hi> 24, what tends direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to Gods glory, conſtancy in that is a commendation. <hi>David</hi> never changed his purpoſe of building the houſe of the Lord, <hi>Psal,</hi> 132, 4.5. And of paying his Vows, <hi>Pſal,</hi> 66, 13, 14 2. Be well acquaint with the word, The word of the Lord to ſome is a reproach, they have no delight in it, they mock it, <hi>Jer,</hi> 6, 10. Such are the plague of their Generation, in the word the rules of Government are inſert, the ſins and ſnares of Rulers are related, the examples of good, and bade are propoſed, for imitation and caution: You would examine all inſtructions of Men, by the injunctions of the word, and ſteer your courſe by this compaſs, if you would Land fair when you go off the ſtage of time. 3. Have a good care of the ſtate, it will never be well with the Kirk if it be not well with the ſtate <hi>Psal</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:62741:12"/>laſt, <hi>the wicked walk on every ſide, when vileſt men are exalted;</hi> Some endangers crowned heads, and runs them on precipices; Kings ſhould make choice of Favorites, <hi>men fearing God, loving truth, hating covetouſnes, Exod,</hi> 18, 21. <hi>Psal,</hi> ioi, 2, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
               <q rend="margQuotes">I will behave my ſelf wiſely in a perfect way, O when wilt thou come unto me:</q> I will walk within my houſe with a perfect heart; he looked well to his Court and his Family, he abandoned the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull workers, and made choiſe of the Faithfull of the land. 4. Be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to make good Laws, conform to the word of God, the law of laws, and that there be vigorous execution of good Laws, made, or to be made which is the life of the Law, Laws are not for <hi>Theory,</hi> but for <hi>Practice,</hi> the beſt practice on the Peoples part, is obedience, on the Magiſtrats part, is execution, duly and impartially applying rewards and Puniſhments. Cruel were theſe Laws <hi>Daniel.</hi> 3, and 6, Chapters, and Act 4, and 5, Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, forbidding Preaching, prayer, and worſhip to God; we have ſmarted under ſome ſuch grievous Laws; the vigorous execution of cruel Laws, broke the work of Reformation, God forbid the ſlack or none execution of good Laws, ſhould ruine it once more. I muſt warne you all who hears me, if any of you has had a hand in the l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>te Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feution, directly or indirectly, in leſs or in more, in Fining, Confin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Impriſonment, Baniſhment, Torture, Intercommuning, Shedding of Blood, Repent or dear ſhall you buy it. 5. Your chief care would be about Religious concerns, to advance <hi>Zions</hi> welfare, as <hi>David</hi> by vow and Oath ſhews his concernment <hi>Psal,</hi> i32. 1. Let not what concerns <hi>Zion</hi> be reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a by-work, ſo did not <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 137, 4. He preferred <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to his chief joy, and, as with a curſe, wiſhed that he might neither have Skill nor power to Act, if he ſhould forget or ſlight <hi>Zion</hi> 2: Mind how God reſents and ſpeaks with contempt, of thoſe who poſtponed the building of the Temple (which was the principal fruit and end of their deliverance,) to the building of their own houſes, and tells plainly, they ſhould not thrive the better of it, what they earned, they ſhould put it in a bag with holes, <hi>Mag,</hi> 1.6.3. Mind the example of the <hi>Jews,</hi> when they were ſtirred up to build the Temple, <hi>Ezra.</hi> 5, i, 2. They ſay not, we muſt firſt build the Walls of <hi>Jerusalem.</hi> to hold out the enemy, but they began to build the houſe of God; happy theſe who are ſo diſpoſed to promot the publick inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of the Church more than their own. 4 For your own ſakes be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in the Lords intereſts, and he will be concerned in you in theſe five Reſpects. i. He will be concerned in your honour; The Lord reſents the indignity done to Magiſtrats, and Stigmatizeth theſe who deſpiſe Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:62741:12"/>and ſpeak evil of dignities <hi>Jude</hi> 8 <q rend="margQuotes">Theſe that honour me, I will honour, who deſpiſeth me ſhall be lightly eſteemed. <bibl>1 <hi>Sam,</hi> 2, 30,</bibl>
               </q> 2. He will be concerned in your houſe and Family, 1. <hi>Chron,</hi> 1, 13 14. The Lord bleſſed the houſe of <hi>Obed-Edom</hi> and all that he had, becauſe of the Ark of God; And the Lord promiſes. 2 <hi>Sam,</hi> 7. To build <hi>David</hi> a ſure Houſe, becauſe of his reſpect to his houſe. 3. The Lord will be concerned in your thriving <hi>Psal,</hi> i22 6. They ſhall proſper that love <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> ſo did <hi>Moses, Joſhua</hi> and others proſper upon this Account. 4. The Lord will be concerned in your ſafety in a dangerous time; when the Lord threatned old and young by a Deſtroying Angel, he allows a mark of providential preſervation to be ſet on ſuch, <hi>Ezek,</hi> 9.4, 5 The Lord will be concerned in your Conſolation, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 66 10, Such Perſons ſhall ſhare of <hi>Jerusalems</hi> joy. 5, Loſe not a Seaſon of doing ſervice to the Church, and eaſing her of what is grievous; There is a hazard in this <hi>Eccles:</hi> 10, ſo, what thy hand finds to do, do it with all thy might, for there is no work nor device in the grave; you wot not if ever another opportunity be put in ſome of your hands: Some are off the ſtage, who loſed a Seaſon, you may rue it out of time, do what remains, and is needfull to be done for advancing the work of God; remember what <hi>Mordecay</hi> ſays to <hi>Eſther Eſth.</hi> 4.14. <q rend="margQuotes">If thou hold thy peace at this time, then ſhall there enlargment and deliverance come to the Jews from another place, but thou and thy Fathers Houſe ſhall be deſtroyed, and who knows whether thow art come to the Kingdom for ſuch a time as this;</q> If you be inconcerned in his matters, he will be als inconcerned in you, and break you if you prefer your own houſe to <hi>his</hi> 6, In order to this, promote piety, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, By your commands as <hi>Aſa</hi> 2. <hi>Chron</hi> 14.2.4, He did that which was good and right in the Eyes of the Lord his God, and commanded <hi>Judah</hi> to ſeek the Lord God of their Fathers, and to do the Law and commandement: And <hi>Joſiah</hi> 2, <hi>Chron.</hi> 34. Covenanted the people to walk after the Lord. 2 By the example of your perſons and Families, as did <hi>'David</hi> and <hi>Joſhua ſal.</hi> 101, and <hi>Joſhua</hi> 24, For this end ſtrive to get divine principles, according to theſe, will your actions be, Let God's Statues be the men of your Council, and his Glory, the end of your actions; <hi>Conſtantius,</hi> the Father of <hi>Conſlantine,</hi> tried his Courtiers wiſely; who adhered to truth, he honoured them; who fore-ſook Chriſt them he degraded &amp; ſaid, who were falſe to God, would never be true to him: Much depends on Magiſtrats their perſonal carriage and their Courts; Lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of people eaſily cauſes them to erre <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 9.16, One wicked man in au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority deſtroyes much good, <hi>Eccls</hi> 9, 18, Their example is ſo powerfull
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:62741:13"/>3, Encourage and ſtrengthen the hands of painfull, faithfull Miniſters; men according to Gods own Heart, 4, Diſcountenance what ſmels of ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion and Jdolatry; Wee are glad that courſe has been taken, and will be far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther taken by his Majeſties Honourable Privy Council, to eaſe the Land of <hi>Jeſuit Prieſts,</hi> the Grand trafficquers, who infuſe the Venome of cruel and damnable principles, the fopperys of ſuperſtitious and unſcriptural conceits and have been, and are the principal abetters of horrid cruelties; Such have been too much carreſſed by many 4. Have a fervent care to look well to ſeminaries of Learning; It's an old trick of <hi>Rome</hi> to poiſon the fountains that the ſtreams may be mudded; Much depends on the piety, principles, and example of <hi>Maſters,</hi> young ones may ſoon get a wrong ſet that will not eaſily cure; It's dangerous to ſuck in poyſon with milk. 5. Be carefull of the eſtabliſhed Government of the Church, which we own as founded on the word of God, in which theſe five things are expreſſe. 1 Anent its Officers as ye have them diſtinguiſhed <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.11, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.12. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17. <hi>Act.</hi> 6, And not a <hi>Prelat</hi> among them all. 2. Its Courts and Judicatories <hi>Matth.</hi> 18, 16.18, It was no civil Courts meant there. 3. Subordination of Leſſer Judicatories to Greater <hi>Acts</hi> 15.4. Wee have the order of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedure in relation to cenſure <hi>Matth</hi> 18.16. 5. The naturall kind of theſe cenſures, not Bodily but Spiritual; And there is a Charge to obſerve all theſe things inviolable untill Chriſt ſecond coming 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.21.1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.14 Wee moſt ſay, that the <hi>Scots</hi> ſoil could never agree with <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latick</hi> nor <hi>Eraſtian</hi> domination: This government was owned by Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours from moſt of the reformed Churches of Europe at the ſynod of <hi>Dort</hi> and ſubcrived by them all ſave two; it was ſolemnly ſworn to be perſons of all ranks in this Nation an Hundered yeares ago; It is moſt adapted to the ends of an Eſtabliſhed Miniſtry to edify Souls and to guard againſt vice and errour <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.11.12.</p>
            <p>Beware of what may give a Back-ſet to this Government &amp; is grievuees to it for I may venture to ſay in <hi>Scotland</hi> there is ſo ſtrong a twiſt in the preſent eſtabliſhment bet wixt Kirk and State that they may reckon heart friends &amp; foes together that who are Heart-friends to the State will be freinds to the Kirk as now eſtabliſhed for I Judge it will be found, friends to this intereſt will be found in Scotland, <hi>His Majeſties</hi> beſt Friends if not His only Friends whatever others pretends for their own ſafety advantage or advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Our readines to venture and offer in a dangerous Juncture is not unknown: <hi>I</hi> may ſay in Scotland if <hi>King William</hi> had a ſtrait they would make but a ſmall <hi>Batalion</hi> of truſties that would be found on the other ſide;
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:62741:13"/>I neither think nor ſpeak ſo of <hi>England,</hi> how many there of the Epiſcopal perſwaſion, have given, and do give pregnant proofs of their Loyaltie, &amp; good affection to <hi>The King,</hi> beyond all exception.</p>
            <p>There has been a great work about taking in of Conformiſts in <hi>Scotland</hi> to the Government, but how have they ſlighted the condeſcendency of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, to make application and qualify themſelves? Yea they are imbold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the forbearance of Church and State; nor have wee taken the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage allowed, not that we are for Cruelty, but for Charity, which we have extended to ſome for their ſupply, and inclines yet to do ſo, wiſhing that the moſt needy and beſt affected might ſhare of the Charity of all, yet are wee not fond of medling with them, knowing their temper; There are a number taken in by us, I deny not, there may be ſome more ſober, Serious, and deſerves more incouragement than others; I judge we are through the throng of them, and wiſhes they be all ſound at the heart: For thoſe we received in the North, if there be truth in Men, wee had ground to think, they would be true to their truſt: For others in the North, we found their pulſe, that they were neither Friends to Kirk nor State; In ſtead of Application, they ruſhed in on the Committee, unmannerly, being neither cited nor called, and gave in Proteſtations diſowning the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Church, and ſpitting in the face of the Law for our eſtabliſhment, altho' under the colour of a fair complement to the State; A meer pretext, no more to be truſted then <hi>Joabs</hi> ſimulat complement to <hi>Amaſa</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 20.3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>0. Who, under the covert of a fair Brotherly Salutation, intended a deadly wound, which he gave him under the fifth Rib, and ſhed out his Bowels to the ground; Some of theſe are declared <hi>Intruders,</hi> illegally ſetled, ſome of them Lybelled for <hi>Scandals.</hi> And its known from the North eſpecially, there were offers in a <hi>Formula,</hi> repeated Addreſſes to <hi>His Majesty,</hi> Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to the laſt Seſſion of Parliament, declaring themſelves ready and willing to joyn with the preſent Church Government; Yet in their Proteſtations, they pretend to give Reaſons, why in conſcience they cannot do it; where is their ground of Truſt? Judge how well contrived they are, made up of Contradictions; Now if ſuch Men who Savour of <hi>Tobia's</hi> and <hi>Sanballat</hi>'s com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion, ſhould offer to feign Subjection, with a mind to undermind the work it were no wonder we were ſhy to deal with them: And for thoſe who at beſt declare their indifferency for any Government the State appoints eſpecially conſidering how guilty they are of coutradictory Oaths ſubverſive of the Government; Who can truſt they will ſupport it; and not ſubvert if? A cold and feigned friend may ſoon turn an Enemy; can we be blamed
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:62741:14"/>being convinced they are generally Enemies to Kirk and State to decline ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting, with them: A King would be thought ill adviſed, to take and keep in his boſom, Men whoſe diſaffection and inclinations, ſubverſive of his Government and intereſt, might be evidenced to a demonſtration: For ſome of us, before wee cloſed with ſuch, we would rather chuſe to take our old venture to ſeek our Bread with the peril of our Lives.</p>
            <p>I will crave your pardon and patience, in all Soberneſs to repreſent a few grievous things. 1. That thoſe who neither comply with Kirk nor State meet in pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ended Presbytries and Synods, and act as Legal Jud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>catories, and obtrude Men of their way on vacant Churches: 2, Many of them who refuſe to own the Government of Kirk and State, take on them to preach irregularly, Baptize Children, and even of Scandalous perſons, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to the removing of the Scandal; And Marry perſons claudeſtinly, without knowledge or conſent of Parents: Who are ſecure of their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren at this rate? And they Marry ſome perſons, within forbidden degrees, and ſome whole former Mariages are not diſolved; ſome of them anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date Teſtimonials, and abſolve perſons in whom they have no intereſt, ſome of them have likeways brought in <hi>innovations</hi> in worſhip, never uſed under any Government of Proteſtants in <hi>Scotland:</hi> And farther, contrair to all order and in manifeſt contempt of Church Cenſures, ſeveral depoſed for groſs in moralities, Conturnacy, &amp; Supine-negligence, continue in all the parts of the Miniſterial function, which in ſome places breeds a great dale of confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and diſorder; theſe things we can inſtruct if need be; From all which flows and a bounds prophaneſs, Irreligion, and Atheiſm, notwithſtanding of all the excellent Laws made againſt them.</p>
            <p>Now it's in the power of your hands to order remedies for all theſe things, by applying the Laws made, and to be made in Church-matters, and incouraging the Church in her Liberties, and all her Aſſemblies: I would exhort all the Members of this Honourable Court, As ye would prove your ſelves to walk in truth and with a perfect heart, in your Spheres and Capaciti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, prove your ſelves <hi>Nurſing Fathers</hi> to the Church, and guard againſt thoſe who would poiſon or ſtarve the Flocks, and overthrow the Government of the Lords houſe.</p>
            <p>I do here declare, I did not intend to irritat any Man; I dare not be a <hi>Man-pleaſer,</hi> for then I ſhould not be the Servant of Chriſt, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.10. But <hi>I</hi> reſolved to exoner my Conſcience in the fight of God, who is your Maſter and mine, if I ſhould never Preach more; Now, as you will all anſwer before Him, conſider what I have ſaid, for there is a day of Compt and Reckoning coming.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:62741:14"/>
            <p>My hearty Prayer to God is, That <hi>His Majesties high Commiſſioner,</hi> and all the Members of this Houourable Court, may be helped by Grace ſo to behave, As in that Great Day, You may all meet with that ſweet welcome, Well done Good and Faithful Servants, enter into Your Maſters Joy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The Lord grant You underſtanding in all theſe things, To His name be Praiſe.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
